{"tossups": [{}, {"question": "<b>Gherman Lopatin and Pyotr Yakubovich led largely unsuccessful efforts to resurrect this organization after its most famous action. This organization considered itself the successor</b> <b>to the (+)</b> <b>\u201cgoing to the people\u201d movement and it splintered from the Land and Liberty</b> <b>organization, disagreeing with its focus on propaganda. Sophia Perovskaya was the first woman (*) </b> executed for terrorism after she led this organization in an action where Nikolai Rysakov and Ignacy Hrenieweisky threw bombs at a carriage. For the points, name this socialist revolutionary terrorist group which assassinated Tsar Alexander II.", "answer": "The<b> People\u2019s Will</b> (accept<b> Narodnaya Volya</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This state\u2019s Annual Customs involves a human sacrifice practice called the Xwetanu or\u201cyearly head business,\u201d where victims were ritually beheaded. King Ghezo was blockaded by the British over this state\u2019s (+) slave trade, despite having come to power with the help of trader Francisco Felix de Sousa. This state conquered the Whydah Kingdom but was sometimes a tributary to the (*) </b> Oyo Empire. The Mino or Amazons was the all-female combat regiment of this state, who fought in an 1892 to 1894 war against the French. For the points, name this West African kingdom centered around Abomey in modern-day Benin.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Dahomey</b> (do not accept of prompt on \u201cKingdom of Benin\u201d) Page 1", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>With the help of Quintus Anicius Faustus, this ruler expanded the</b><em><b> Limes Tripolitanus</b></em><b> to protect against attacking nomads. This man ordered that Hannibal\u2019s tomb be covered with</b> <b>fine marble shortly after his general (+)</b> <b>Publius Cornelius conquered the Cilician pass.</b> <b>Upon taking power, this man discharged the Praetorian Guard and replaced them with his own legions. This man advised his sons to (*)</b> \u201cbe harmonious, enrich the soldiers, and scorn all other men\u201don his deathbed. He outlasted Pescennius Niger and Clodius Albinus to take power in the Year of the Five Emperors. For the points, identify this father of Caracalla, known as \u201cthe African emperor.\u201d", "answer": "Septimius<b> Severus</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>One work of this type describes the heretical theology of a 16th century miller named Menocchio and is by Carlo Ginzburg. Another work of this type by Natalie Davis investigates how peasants constructed identity and argues that (+) Bertrande defended Arnauld du Tilh despite knowing he was an imposter because society required her to have a husband. This type of work strives to \u201csee the world in a (*)</b> grain of sand\u201d by using exemplary ordinary people to discuss wider trends. The<em> Cheese and the Worms</em> and<em> The Return of Martin Guerre</em> are examples of, for the points, what methodological genre of small-scale history?", "answer": "<b> microhistory</b> Page 2", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s daughter Elizabeth wrote the New Mexico state song. Carl Adamson may have killed this man, though others believe Archie \u201cPrint\u201d Rhode did it. Jesse Wayne</b> <b>Brazel was defended from charges of murdering this man by (+)</b> <b>Albert Fall. Territorial</b> <b>Governor George Curry denied this man a position after he lived with El Paso prostitute (*)</b> \u201cMrs. Brown\u201d. One of Teddy Roosevelt\u2019s three \u201cWhite House Gunslingers\u201d, this man investigated the disappearance of Albert Jennings Fountain and killed fugitive Norman Newman. During the Lincoln County War, a subject asked this man at Fort Sumner, \u201cQui\u00b4en es?\u201d before this man killed William Bonney. For the points, name this sheriff from New Mexico who killed Billy the Kid.", "answer": "Pat<b> Garrett</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In one of this author\u2019s works, Christopher Banks is trapped in the Japanese invasion</b> <b>of Shanghai before finding out his mother was seized as a concubine by Wang (+)</b> <b>Ku. In</b> <b>another work by this author, the main characters journey to Norfolk, where they believe lost things can be found, to investigate a \u201cpossible.\u201d In that work, one character is informed the art he created at (*)</b> Hailsham was insufficient to prove he has a soul or grant him an deferral on his organ donation. For the points, what recent Nobel Laureate author of When We Were Orphans wrote about the clones Ruth, Tommy, and Kathy in Never Let Me Go?", "answer": "Sir Kazuo<b> Ishiguro</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "<b>Sir Robert Filmer claimed that Adam was the first person to whom this idea applied and compared this idea to the authority exercised by a father in his work</b><em><b> Patriarcha</b></em><b>. Jacques-B\u00b4enigne (+) Bossuet used Solomon as an example in a sermon defending this idea, </b><em><b>Politics Drawn from the Very Words of the Holy Scripture</b></em><b>. This idea forms the basis for the dual nature of the head of the body politic. This idea was attacked by (*)</b> social contract theorists, who argued that rulers answered to their subjects. For the points, name this idea which stated that a monarch\u2019s legitimacy to rule was derived solely from God.", "answer": "<b> Divine Right</b> of Kings Page 3", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Walter Duranty described this event as \u201cmostly bunk\u201d in \u201csome of the worst reporting to appear in\u201d the New York Times. One country responded to Cardinal Theodor Innitzer</b> <b>during this event by stating that \u201cthere are neither (+)</b> <b>cardinals or cannibals\u201d in this</b> <b>event\u2019s country, despite also publishing a poster stating \u201cto eat your own children is a barbarian act.\u201d Possession of (*)</b> food was considered evidence of stealing during this event in which the Red Army isolated an area including Kharkiv and Odessa Oblasts. For the points, name this 1933 famine engineered by Stalin and recognized as a genocide against ethnic Ukrainians?", "answer": "The<b> Holodomor</b> (or<b> Great Famine</b>,<b> Terror Famine</b>,<b> Ukrainian famine</b>-<b>genocide </b>(accept either genocide or famine) of 1932-1933)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Description acceptable. These people were crushed at the battle of Stone Gate in an</b> <b>1874 retaliatory expedition for the beheading of shipwrecked sailors in the (+)</b> <b>Mudan</b> <b>Incident. A chief of these people named Mona Rudao inadvertently triggered the 1931 Wushe Rebellion by offering blood-soaked wine to a Japanese officer. Chiang Kai-Shek\u2019s (*)</b>\u201cmake mountains like plains\u201d movement attempted to promote Mandarin and nationalism among these people. The Seediq, Amis, and Paiwan are all part of, for the points, what group of indigenous people comprising about two percent of Taiwan\u2019s population?", "answer": "<b> Taiwan</b>ese<b> aborigine</b>s (or<b> Formosa</b> people,<b> Gaoshan</b> people; accept just<b> indigenous people</b>s after \u201cTaiwan\u201d, otherwise prompt on individual tribe names) (16) <b>One project of this group saw a milestone last week with the deployment of a</b> <b>magnetometer boom \u2013 that mission is the culmination of this group\u2019s Horizon 2000+ series</b> <b>and is known as (+)</b> <b>BepiColombo. A facility in Kourou, French Guiana, is central to this</b> <b>organization and is a main site for operation of its (*)</b> Ariane 5 heavy lift vehicle. Probably the best-known missions of this organization are Galileo, a GPS alternative, and the comet orbiter and lander Rosetta. For the points, name this continent-spanning scientific organization that works to launch people and satellites from French Guiana. ANSWER: the<b> E</b>uropean<b> S</b>pace<b> A</b>gency (accept<b> J</b>apan<b> A</b>erospace<b> E</b>xploration<b> A</b>gency before \u201cHorizon 2000+\u201d since BepiColumbo is a joint ESA/JAXA mission) Page 4", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A school of</b><em><b> laissez-faire</b></em><b> economics named after this city supported the Anti-Corn Law League, which was headquartered in this city. One group organized a march from this city to London to protest the suspension of the Habeas Corpus Act and was called the (+) Blanketeers. Friedrich Engel\u2019s observations in this city formed the basis of his</b><em><b> The Condition </b><b>of the Working Class in England</b></em><b>. The many textile mills in this city led it to be called (*)</b>\u201cCottonopolis\u201d. The 15th Hussars charged a demonstration centered on Henry Hunt in this city in the Peterloo Massacre. The Guardian was founded in, for the points, what Industrial Revolution boom town in north-east England?", "answer": "<b> Manchester</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s friend Enrique Queralt resigned after seeing this man rig a 11-1 win at the Chamartin stadium in a cup tournament. Athletic Club was forced to abandon their (+)\u201ccantera\u201d system of recruitment under this man. This leader was accused of pressuring River Plate to sell (*)</b> Alfredo di Stefano to his favored team. His backing of Santiago Bernabeu led to sixteen league titles and the first \u201cGalacticos\u201d era. For the points, identify this ardent supporter of Real Madrid, the generalissimo of Spain for nearly four decades.", "answer": "Francisco<b> Franco</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This piece begins with a strong descending F-D flat-C-B flat motif before transitioning to a lyrical D-flat minor theme. Nikolai Rubenstein refused to premiere this piece, which</b> <b>was instead premiered by Hans von B\u00a8ulow in 1875 in Boston. Nikita (+)</b> <b>Khrushchev</b> <b>replied \u201cIs he the best? Then give him the prize!\u201d after judges asked if they could award first prize to an American who had performed this piece at the inaugural (*) </b> competition named for this piece\u2019s composer. Van Cliburn earned an 8 minute standing ovation in Moscow during Cold War with, for the points, what piece by Peter Tchaikovsky?", "answer": "<b> Tchaikovsky Piano Concerto</b> No. 1 in B-flat Minor", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>D. Michael Quinn cited the proclamation \u201cvengeance is mine and I have taken a little\u201das evidence that a man was responsible for this event. The only man executed for this event</b> <b>declared he had been (+)</b> <b>\u201csacrificed in a cowardly, dastardly manner.\u201d James Henry (*)</b> Carleton led an investigation into this event, during which he found the bones of small children secretly buried by Jacob Hamblin. The \u201cConfessions of John D. Lee\u201d detailed his participation in this event as a member of the Nauvoo Legion. This event targeted the Baker-Fancher Party and may have been directly ordered by Brigham Young. For the points, name this 1857 massacre of a wagon train by Mormons.", "answer": "<b> Mountain Meadows</b> Massacre", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>During the Battle of El Roble, this man famously said \u201cLads! Live with honor, or die with glory! He who is brave, follow me\u201d. This man fought his ally Luis Carrera at the Battle</b> <b>of (+)</b> <b>Las Tres Acequias, and he was later defeated by Mariano Osorio at the Battle of</b> <b>Rancaqua. After crossing the (*)</b> Andes, this man and his ally Jose de San Martin won the Battles of Chacabuco and Maipu, leading to the capture of Santiago and the liberation of his home country. For the points, name this Chilean independence leader and Second Supreme Director of Chile.", "answer": "Bernardo<b> O\u2019Higgins</b> (NHBB Nats) Page 6", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>While walking on a promenade near this body of water, Empress Elisabeth of Austra was stabbed by anarchist Luigi Lucheni. According to Gregory of Tours, a tsunami developed</b> <b>in this lake in the 6th century, destroying a fort at (+)</b> <b>Taurendunum. The Strait of</b> <b>Promenthoux separates this lake into two parts, the \u201cLittle Lake\u201d and the \u201cGreat Lake.\u201dThe city of (*) </b> Vevey lies on the northern shore of this lake and is home to Nestle\u2019s international headquarters. The Dranse and Rhone river flows into, for the points, which lake that shares its name with a Western Swiss city?", "answer": "Lake<b> Geneva</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>Workers on this project included Dr. Henri Hekking, who became famous for his ability to improvise medicinal cures from plants. At the part of this construct that crossed the (+) Tenasserim Hills, workers were forced to cut rock by torchlight in the Hellfire Pass. The most famous part of this construct spanned the Mae Klong River and was known as the (*)</b>\u201cbridge over the Kwai.\u201d This construct stretched from Ban Pong to Thanbyuzayat after its completion in 1943. For the points, Japan built what railway that linked Bangkok with Rangoon during WWII?", "answer": "<b> Burma Railway</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The extent of this organization\u2019s HVA operations was revealed by the Rosenholz files. Police inspector Karl-Heinz Kurras shot a collaborator with this organization named (+) Benno Ohnesorg during a 1967 student protest. Photo manipulation and wiretapping were frequently used for this organization\u2019s psychological warfare program called \u201c</b><em><b>zersetzung</b></em><b>.\u201dMarkus Wolf employed (*)</b> Gunter Guillaume to spy on Chancellor Willy Brandt for this organization, prompting Brandt\u2019s humiliating resignation in 1974. ftp name this notorious East German secret police force, which frequently collaborated with the Soviet KGB.", "answer": "<b> Stasi</b> or<b> M</b>inistry<b> f</b>or<b> S</b>tate Security or<b> State Security Service</b> (<b>S</b>taat<b>s</b>sicherheits<b>d</b>ienst)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Thirteen St. Louis people with this disease died after being accidentally treated with contaminated horse blood. That incident involving this disease helped lead to the passage of the Biologics Control Act. In 1925, Leonhard Seppala took a shortcut across Norton (+) Sound to deliver serum against this disease. During that event, the \u201cGreat Race of Mercy,\u201dTogo and Balto traversed across (*) </b> Alaska to help quell an epidemic of this disease in Nome. Children are vaccinated against pertussis and tetanus alongside, for the points, what disease, which caused an outbreak whose curing is commemorated by the Iditarod.", "answer": "<b> diphtheria</b> Page 7", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One painting depicts this man in the Armenian Saint Nicholas Monastery in an attempt to discredit rumors that he poisoned a group of 50 incurable men. That painting by Baron Gros shows this man (+) \u201cVisiting the Plague Victims of Jaffa.\u201d Another painting focused on this man shows his mother Maria Ramolino in a position more prominent than that of the (*)</b> pope, despite her absence from the central event. That painting of this man\u2019s \u201cCoronation\u201d was created by Jacques-Louis David. For the points, name this man whose final defeat in 1815 is depicted in paintings of the Battle of Waterloo.", "answer": "<b> Napoleon</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s foreign standing was hurt by the death of his adviser William Shakespear at Jarrab. This man signed the Treaty of (+) Darin, becoming a protectorate of Britain in exchange for declaring war against the Rashid clan. He won the Battle of Sabilla to secure power against the Ikhwan militia and was able to spread his (*)</b> Wahhabi doctrine as a result of a 1938 oil boon in his country. This man\u2019s descendants included Faisal, Khalid, and the current king Salman. For the points, identify this founder of Saudi Arabia.", "answer": "<b> ibn Saud</b> (accept<b> Abdulaziz</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>One person of this ethnicity became the first female aerial gunnery officer in the Navy</b> <b>while her brother brought a Friendship Bell to (+)</b> <b>San Pedro. A store owned by these</b> <b>people, the Family Red Apple, was picketed with Sonny Carson\u2019s support in the Flatbush boycott. One of these people killed Latasha Harlins, whom she suspected of stealing, leading to attacks on these people\u2019s communities during (*)</b> \u201cSa-I-Gu\u201d, part of the 1992 Rodney King riots. One of these people named Young Kim ran in the 2018 House election. For the points, name these people who might have relatives in Seoul.", "answer": "People of<b> Korea</b>n descent (or<b> Korean</b> - Americans) Page 8", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A city in this state takes its name from the chemical nitrocellulose which it used during</b> <b>World War I to produce tens of thousands of explosives a day. This state\u2019s (+)</b> <b>Kanawha</b> <b>River Valley was contaminated in a 1985 leak at a Union Carbide plant a mere 8 months after the Bhopal disaster. In 2014, (*) </b> Earl Ray Tomblin declared a \u201cstate of emergency\u201d in this state after a Freedom Industries plant spilled hazardous material into the Elk River. For the points, name this state where MCHM, a toxin often used in industrial coal mining, contaminated the water supply of its capital Charleston.", "answer": "<b> West Virginia</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>While holding this position, one man had an area named for him called \u201cLittle Hong Kong\u201d; that man was the 4th Earl of Aberdeen. Under that holder of this position, Richard Pakenham negotiated with (+) James Buchanan to decide the border of Oregon Territory. One holder of this position thoroughly opposed the Munich Agreement as part of the (*)</b>\u201cGlamour Boys\u201d and was Anthony Eden. As holder of this position, Lord Palmerston faced the Affair of the Spanish Marriages and the Don Pacifico affair. Now held by Jeremy Hunt, for the points, name this position in the United Kingdom government that deals with Britain\u2019s affairs with other nations.", "answer": "<b> Foreign Secretary</b> (accept Her Majesty\u2019s Principal<b> Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs</b>) (37) <b>A silver one of these objects was used in Deming, New Mexico, after a piece of</b> <b>infrastructure was completed by Charles Crocker\u2019s company. Alexander Ross took a picture</b> <b>of Donald Alexander Smith (+)</b> <b>driving in one of these objects that featured the presence</b> <b>of Governor General Henry Petty-Fitzmaurice on a project that James Ross had engineered through Kicking Horse Pass. The Lucin (*)</b> Cutoff avoids one location where this object was used, which was shown in an A.J. Russell image that notably does not depict any Asian workers at Promontory Summit. The locomotive<em> Jupiter</em> was part of a ceremony including Leland Stanford driving in, for the points, what type of golden object on the Transcontinental Railroad? ANSWER: Last<b> Spike</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The</b> <b>Model Industries Building on this island is located to the west of the New Industries</b> <b>Building. The (+)</b> <b>Agave Trail showcases the wildlife on this island. During World War I,</b> <b>Philip Grosser was kept on this island due to his (*)</b> conscientious objecter status. Frank Morris, John Anglin, and Clarence Anglin, escape from a location on this island. For the points, name this island in San Francisco Bay which housed a US Federal Prison until 1963.", "answer": "<b> Alcatraz</b> Island Page 10", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}], "bonuses": []}